operationsmile.org 2019-12-11

# Privacy Policy | Operation Smile

## **PRIVACY POLICY**

At Operation Smile we value and respect the privacy of our supporters and visitors.  

We strongly believe in protecting the integrity of the information gathered from our supporters and visitors throughout each of our communication channels, including our website, and only using such information as it pertains to improving overall user experience and in pursuit of our mission. We take your privacy extremely seriously, and will never sell or rent lists or email addresses. We are also committed to making sure information you provide is accurate and updated.  

By visiting operationsmile.org and/or any associated subdomains, online services, and/or mobile applications, you are accepting the standards and practices described in this Privacy Policy. This policy applies to all the pages hosted on this site and does not apply to pages hosted by other Operation Smile affiliates, linked organizations, partners, or to other organizations to which we may provide a link and whose privacy policies may differ.  

If you disagree with any of the terms herein, please immediately discontinue use of the Sites. This policy may be changed or updated, so please review it periodically to ensure you stay informed of those changes.  

If you have any questions about our Privacy Policy, or you are concerned information we have related to your personal information is inaccurate or out dated, you can contact us at: 

3641 Faculty Boulevard 

Virginia Beach, VA 23453 USA 

Tel: 888-677-6453 

Fax: (757) 321-7663 

Email:  [drelations@operationsmile.org](mailto:drelations@operationsmile.org)  

### **Information We Collect and Use**  

Operation Smile, like most website owners, receives and records information from various sources as it relates to your interaction with Operation Smile owned sites and digital properties. The type of information we and/or our third party providers collect depends on the interaction between you and us.  This could be when making a donation, applying for a job/to volunteer or through an online purchase.  We gather information through postal communications, visits to our websites or apps, participation with our business/corporate partners, electronic communications, volunteering or communications through social media. We and/or our third party providers may also collect information publicly available through third party platforms (such as online social media platforms), online databases, or that is otherwise legitimately obtained.   Operation Smile is the sole owner of any information collected on this site. This information is used solely for our own data analysis, audits, enhancing or improving user experience and donor acquisition and retention purposes. We will not sell, share (except possibly with another Operation Smile affiliate when it is required to carry out the transactions you initiate), or rent this information to others in ways different from what is disclosed in this statement. We will use reasonable efforts to (1) undertake a privacy impact assessment whenever there is a fundamental change in the way we process data, (2) implement records management systems, and (3) log data security incidents. We will only release personal information to another person or company with your consent, or to the extent required by law. 

Operation Smile collects personally identifiable information from site visitors, supporters and other constituencies through first-party voluntary interaction with Operation Smile. This may include data users choose to enter through registration, making a donation or purchase online or offline, subscribing to our e-newsletter, taking an action, submitting a survey, applying for a job, or any other action that requires direct input by a user.   By providing this input, user is consenting to Operation Smile’s use of the personal information as described in this Privacy Policy. 

Keeping this personal information secure is a top priority for Operation Smile. Personal information is private and confidential; accordingly, the information provided is stored in a secure location, is accessible only by designated employees, trained in the proper handling of customer information, and is used only for the purpose for which the information is collected. Whenever Operation Smile should hire other organizations to provide support services, we will require them to conform to our privacy standards and allow us to audit them for compliance.  

In addition to data users voluntarily provide, Operation Smile uses third party services and platforms, such as Google Analytics, to place first party and/or third party cookies or similar technologies on devices that access Operation Smile owned properties that may collect and record non-identifying/aggregated information on user interactions.  Operation Smile uses this aggregated data to determine and monitor usage characteristics and activities of visitors to evaluate and improve a user’s experience and for guiding market decisions.  The collected data is NOT personally identifiable and therefore cannot be tied back to an individual user. To learn more about what data Google Analytics collects and options to opt-out visit the Analytics support page: <https://support.google.com/analytics/answer/6004245?hl=en>  

Operation Smile and its digital properties also use third-party advertising companies such as Google, Bing, Facebook, Yahoo, among others, to serve advertisements that may be of interest to you when you access and use sites, applications and properties across devices, websites and offline mediums, based on information relating to your access to and use of Operation Smile digital properties. To do so, these companies may place or recognize unique “cookies” or pixel tags on your computer’s browser or use other interaction data from Operation Smile.   For more information on “cookies” please see section “About Cookies.”  For more information on third party digital advertising and to opt-out please visit: http://www.aboutads.info/choices/ or http://optout.networkadvertising.org/.   You may also visit https://www.facebook.com/help to opt out certain of Facebook advertising. If located in the European Union click <http://www.youronlinechoices.eu/>[ ](http://www.youronlinechoices.eu/)

Operation Smile occasionally uses third party service providers and/or sources, among other things, to analyze and use personally identifiable interactions on our website and other digital properties to update bad or insufficient account information such as email address, physical address, and phone number, to provide a better experience to constituents and supporters. 

### **External Links**  

This website may contain links to other sites. Unless we expressly state otherwise, Operation Smile makes no representations whatsoever concerning the content of those sites. The fact Operation Smile has provided a link to a site is not an endorsement, authorization, sponsorship, or affiliation with respect to such site, its owners, or its providers. There are risks associated with using any information, software, or products found on the Internet; and, Operation Smile cautions you to make sure you understand these risks before retrieving, using, relying upon, or purchasing anything via the Internet. In addition, we encourage our users to be aware when they leave our site to read the privacy statements of each and every website that collects personally identifiable information. These other sites may collect or solicit personal data or send their own cookies to your computer. Please be aware Operation Smile is not responsible for the information collection, use, disclosure, or security practices (including the data security practices) of other organizations, such as Facebook, Apple, Google, Microsoft, RIM, or any other app developer, app provider, social media platform provider, operating system provider, wireless service provider, or device manufacturer that you may interact with outside of Operation Smile digital properties.  

You may not create a link to this site that incorporates or relies upon, in whole or in part, any content from any page on this website, or that incorporates any copyrighted or other intellectual property of Operation Smile without written permission from Operation Smile Inc.

### **Children’s Privacy**  

Operation Smile is concerned about the protection of online privacy for all our website users. We are particularly respectful of the privacy of our young users. Operation Smile does not knowingly gather and/or use any personally identifiable information from children under the age of 13. You must be 13 years of age or older to access the site. Operation Smile has no interest in collecting information from children under the age of 13. We encourage parents to monitor their children's use of the Internet and to help us protect their privacy by instructing them never to provide personal information on this site or any other without permission. We will never attempt to extract unnecessary information from our users, regardless of age.  Upon request, the parent or guardian of a child under 18 may review and request the deletion of such child’s personally identifiable information, as well as refuse to permit the further collection or use of such information. 

### **Use of  Cookies and Other Technologies ** 

Like most web sites and digital properties, Operation Smile uses "cookies," to obtain certain types of non-personally identifiable information to help improve user experience across Operation Smile properties. 

A cookie is a small text file containing a string of characters that is sent from a web server to your computer when you visit a website, the cookie helps us recognize you when you come back to our site or digital properties. A cookie cannot read data off of your computer hard disk, nor can it read cookie files created by other websites. 

Cookies cannot contain viruses nor install spyware or malware on your computer and are generally used to provide information to the website and server that is useful to improve your experience.  Cookies help make your visit more useful by allowing the website to remember information about your previous visit, like your preferred language, login information, communication preferences, and other settings. Cookies may also be used by Operation Smile and associated third-party advertisers to deliver advertising and marketing across sites and digital properties.  

Operation Smile may also use cookies to aggregate information such as number of visits to our sites or digital properties, average time on site, pages viewed, and other data to improve site experience and performance.   

Operation Smile and its digital properties may use pixel tags, web beacons, or small (usually invisible) blocks of code, attached to a web page, email, or other digital properties that allow us, among others, to  aggregate statistics to measure and evaluate the success of digital properties and/or campaigns. The collected data is NOT personally identifiable and therefore cannot be tied back to an individual user. Operation Smile uses this aggregated data to determine and monitor usage characteristics and activities of visitors to evaluate and improve a user’s experience and for guiding market decisions.   

For more information on cookies and to opt-out visit <http://www.allaboutcookies.org/> or <http://optout.networkadvertising.org/?c=1#!/>. You may also disable the use of cookies by setting your browser to refuse all cookies or to indicate when a cookie is being sent. Be aware, however, some websites may not function properly if you refuse to accept cookies. 

### **Copyright**  

All material on webpages under the domain operationsmile.org, as well as on Operation Smile’s other digital properties is, unless otherwise stated, the property of Operation Smile Inc. These materials are protected by copyright and other intellectual property laws. Information received through this website or digital properties may be displayed, reformatted, and printed for your personal, noncommercial use only. You may not reproduce or retransmit the materials, in whole or in part, in any manner, without the prior written consent of Operation Smile, Inc. The only exception: You may make single copies of the materials available through this website solely for your personal, noncommercial use provide you preserve any copyright or other notices contained in or associated with them and agree not to distribute such copies to others, whether or not in electronic form, whether or not for a charge or other consideration, without prior written consent of Operation Smile Inc., the owner of the materials.

### **Disclaimer and warranties and Liability**  

Because of the number of possible sources of information available through this website, and the inherent hazards and uncertainties of electronic distribution, there may be delays, omissions, or inaccuracies in such information. Operation Smile. cannot and does not warrant the accuracy, completeness, current ness, non-infringement, or fitness for a particular purpose of the information available through this website, nor do we guarantee this website will be error-free or continuously available. 

### **Questions or Suggestions**  

At Operation Smile we respect the opinions and feedback of our visitors and supporters. If you, or other parties have any questions, concerns, or complaints about this policy, or would like to learn more about our organization, please contact us on our website (<https://www.operationsmile.org/contact-us>) or call 1-888-OPSMILE (1- 888-677-6453).

### **Controlling Your Personal Information  ** 

Personal information is information that can identify a person, such as name, address, telephone number, and email address.

We strive for accurate, respectful and relevant communications with our constituents. We occasionally exchange mailing addresses with select non-profit groups. We will not sell, rent or share your email address or telephone number. If you would like to correct or update your personal information, modify your mailing preferences, or if you do not wish to participate in mailing address exchange activities, please call 1-888-OPSMILE (1-888-677-6453) or email [drelations@operationsmile.org](mailto:drelations@operationsmile.org).  

Unsubscribing from specific communications by writing, phoning or emailing us. Please also understand marketing campaigns are scheduled in advance so while we will remove you from the mailing list in a timely manner, you may still receive materials from campaigns which were in process prior to your request to be removed for up to 90 days. 

We respect your time and attention by controlling the frequency of our emails. However, you may modify your email preferences at any time. Each email sent contains an easy, automated way for you to change your expressed interests, or to cease receiving email from us altogether. If you would like to modify your preferences, simply follow the instructions at the end of any email you receive from us, contact us directly or visit your online account page <http://ww2.operationsmile.org/account/>. 

You have the right to request us to update your personal information in the event it is incorrect or out dated. You can do this by contacting [drelations@operationsmile.org](mailto:drelations@operationsmile.org) or calling 1-888-OPSMILE (1- 888-677-6453).

### **Third Party Requests To Change Data  ** 

Except in exceptional circumstances (as outlined in this process) requests to change user information including changes to direct debits, standing orders or any other kind of donation, can only be authorized by the user. We can only take instructions from a third party with the express consent of the user or on evidence of the relevant power of attorney. This is to safeguard the interests of the user with whom we have a relationship.

A request by a third party to remove a user from our mailing list or change mailing preferences may be considered exceptionally if we are convinced the third party is acting in the best interests of the user. This may be a judgment based on the user’s history of giving, any unusual changes in the level of their giving or frequency of giving and any communication we have had with the user regarding their gifts or mailing preferences. Any direct communication from the user (verbal or written) which gives concern that the user may lack capacity to make a sound decision and/or judgment could be taken as support on this. In this context our telemarketing agencies who call on our behalf in fundraising campaigns record conversations with prospective users and where there is a concern relating to mental capacity these recordings could be used by Operation Smile for final decision making. 

### **Is my Information Secure?**  

Keeping your personal information secure is a top priority for Operation Smile. Personal information is private and confidential; accordingly, the information provided is stored in a secure location, is accessible only by designated employees, trained in the proper handling of customer information, and is used only for the purpose for which the information is collected.  

We employ other companies and individuals to perform functions on our behalf. Examples include fulfilling donation receipts and sending postal mail and e-mail, analyzing data, providing marketing assistance, providing search results and links (including paid listings and links), processing credit card payments, and providing customer service. They have access to personal information needed to perform their functions, but may not use it for other purposes. Whenever Operation Smile should hire other organizations to provide support services, we will require them to conform to our privacy standards and allow us to audit them for compliance.  

### **Credit Card Information Security**  

At Operation Smile, we sincerely care about the safety and security of your transaction. We use high grade encryption and the HTTPS security protocol to communicate with your browser software. This method is the industry standard security protocol, which makes it extremely difficult for anyone else to intercept the credit card information you send to us. Companies we work with to process credit card transactions also use high grade encryption and security protocols. Contributions may also be made by calling 1-888-OPSMILE (1- 888-677-6453). 

### **Personal Information Security**  

In addition to maintaining privacy and security controls over information you share with us, Operation Smile works to accurately process your contribution and volunteer information. Operation Smile employs error checking procedures to make certain transactions are processed completely and accurately. As necessary, changes are made to improve our systems. And, independent external and internal audits are conducted to ensure the privacy, security and appropriate processing of your information on our site. During business hours, staff is available to answer questions about your financial donation or personal information at 1-888-OPSMILE (1- 888-677-6453). 

Operation Smile sites and affiliated digital properties are based and operated in the United States.  If you are located outside of the United States, you should be aware that we will collect, process, and maintain your information in the United States.  By using or accessing or providing any information to Operation Smile owned properties (see information collected), you are consenting to the transfer of your information to the United States and accepting that the processing and maintenance of this information which will be done in accordance with this Privacy Policy; further, you are specifically acknowledging we may not offer the same level of privacy protection as your home country would provide. 

## **Consent**  

### **Communications Preferences**  

Operation Smile will not directly market to or solicit to you unless: you have consented to receive direct marketing; you would reasonably expect us to use your personal details as voluntarily provided or acquired through other interactions; or we believe you may be interested in the material but it is impractical for us to obtain your consent. 

We strive for accurate, respectful and relevant communications with our constituents. As such, you may modify or choose how you would like to receive communication from us at any time.  If you choose not to receive communications from us we will honor your choice.  Please also understand marketing campaigns are scheduled in advance so while we will remove you from the mailing list in a timely manner, you may still receive materials from campaigns which were in process prior to your request to be removed for up to 90 days. 

If you would like to correct or update your personal information, modify your communication preferences, or if you do not want to receive any communication from Operation Smile, please call 1-888-OPSMILE (1-888-677-6453) or email [drelations@operationsmile.org](mailto:drelations@operationsmile.org).

### **Email Privacy**  

We are committed to keeping your email address confidential. Operation Smile complies fully with the federal CAN-SPAM Act of 2003. We will not share, sell, rent, lease, swap or authorize any third party to use your email address for any purpose without your permission. We will use your email address solely to communicate information related to Operation Smile and will maintain any information you send via email to us in accordance with applicable federal law. 

If you received an email from us, your email address is either listed with us as someone who has expressly shared this address for the purpose of receiving email communications from us, or you have donated to us, purchased from us or otherwise have been identified as having an existing relationship with us. 

We respect your time and attention by controlling the frequency of our emails. However, you may modify your email preferences at any time. Each email sent contains an easy, automated way for you to change your expressed interests, or to cease receiving email from us altogether. If you would like to modify your preferences, simply follow the instructions at the end of any email you receive from us, contact us directly or visit your online account page <http://ww2.operationsmile.org/account>.

## **Social Media Policy**  

We encourage staff, volunteers and guests to share their medical mission experiences with friends, family and supporters to educate and raise awareness about our organization; please feel free to tag Operation Smile and Operation Smile Student Programs in your posts. We also request that you share stories with us at [socialmedia@operationsmile.org](mailto:socialmedia@operationsmile.org). Please keep in mind that what you say online about your medical mission experience represents Operation Smile. Above all else, we ask that you respect the privacy and dignity of our patients. Your posts should not be discriminatory, offensive, hateful, defamatory or otherwise illegal. Your posts should be culturally sensitive.

### **Our Policies*  ** 

  * Any photo or video you produce will occur with little to no interruption of the medical program.  
  * Do not use copyrighted music in any video or post you publish. Do not use content you create or edit to promote other organizations or companies.  
  * Do not post information about unapproved Operation Smile projects or future projects in development.   

Please refer to our style guide and talking points for more information on how we talk about Operation Smile at: [http://brand.operationsmile.org](http://brand.operationsmile.org/)

### **Our Patients' Dignity  ** 

To uphold Operation Smile’s proprietary information and respect the privacy of our patients, please:  

  * Obtain verbal consent prior to capturing images of patients, volunteers or Operation Smile staff, and be clear about the way that you will be using their image and information.  
  * Do not publish patients’ personal information, including their last names.  
  * Do not publish images of patients who look uncomfortable, frightened or in pain.  
  * Do not publish images of patients who are having their blood drawn, being intubated or extubated, or who have blood around their stitching, face and or medical gown.  
  * Do not post PIT photos. These are photos intended for medical records.  
  * Do not post immediate post-operative photos of patients.  
  * Be respectful of patients who are undergoing anesthesia or who are waking up from anesthesia.  
  * Be respectful of patients who are partially clothed or unclothed.  
  * Be mindful of the words used in your post. Do not refer to a patient as a “cleft patient.” Say instead, “a patient born with a cleft condition” or something similar. In posts, do not refer to their cleft condition as a “deformity”; while this may be a medical term, our patients have told us they do not appreciate this word being used casually.  
  * Do not publish images of patients who have poor lip revision scars. Often, these patients did not receive surgical care from our medical teams, and without the proper context, this could be a poor reflection of our work.  

Do not criticize the work of other surgical organizations. 

### **Your Safety  ** 

  * Do not post political views or discuss political issues within the host country.  
  * Do not post your travel itinerary.  
  * Do not post the personal opinions of other Operation Smile staff or volunteers.   
  * Do not post inappropriate photos of yourself, team members or patients that may be perceived as unprofessional, culturally insensitive or offensive, or violating a patient's right to privacy.  
  * Do check-in during emergency situations.   

_*OPERATION SMILE RESERVES THE RIGHT TO ASK YOU TO REMOVE DIGITAL CONTENT RELATED TO THE ORGANIZATION, ITS PROGRAMS AND PATIENTS AT ANY TIME, FOR ANY REASON._  

Updated: May 25, 2018
